Introduction to Computer Skills
103
Supplement to 111. Teaches skills needed, e.g. using command-line, file systems, debugging. Primarily for students with less experience in using computers.
Charles Hedrick
True
False
Great Insights in Computer Science
105
The class is a tour of the big ideas that make computer science an academic discipline. We tour the architecture of modern computers from bits and logic all the way up to programming languages and software libraries. We probe the insights in computability and algorithm design that make possible massive search engines like Google and help us understand the relation between computation and intelligence. Coursework primarily involves paper-and-pencil problem solving and a very small amount of programming to provide students with hands-on-experience with the concepts we introduce.
Casimir Kulikowski
False
True
Computing for Math and the Sciences
107
This course is designed to introduce the student to computers, programming, and some of the key ideas on which the field of computer science is based. The primary vehicle for doing so is the computer language MATLAB. The use of a program like MAPLE to manipulate symbolic equations is also covered. This course is aimed at students majoring in math or in a physical science.
Douglas Motto
True
True
Principles of Computer Science
110
Computer Science concepts are relevant to many aspects of our lives, from explorations in the fields of science and medicine to digital creations in the fields of art and music. This course introduces students to the central ideas of computer science and explores technologies of computing and their impact on society and culture. ßStudents are introduced to web site design, data investigation and manipulation using spreadsheets, collaborative on-line tools, and fundamental computer programming concepts. ßStudents develop computational skills and are engaged in the creative aspects of problem solving through programming. Students investigate the global impacts and social implications of computing innovations, data, and the Internet through discussions, projects, and writing.
Frances Trees
True
True
Introduction to Computer Science
111
Intensive introduction to computer science. Problem solving through decomposition. Writing, debugging, and analyzing programs in Java. Algorithms for sorting and searching. Introduction to data structures, recursion.
Ana Centeno
True
False
Data Structures
112
To investigate the essential properties of data structures and algorithms for operating on them; to use these structures as tools to assist algorithm design; to extend exposure to searching, sorting and hashing techniques.
Sesh Venugopal, Juan Zhai
False
False
Data 101: Data Literacy
142
This class aims to provide you with a basic set of tools for data literacy as well as general view of the impact of data on society and elements of common sense data analysis and reasoning. ß A significant piece of the class will be learning foundations of ßR. R is a statistical software environment and programming language that we╞ll use to analyze and visualize datasets. ßLearning simple R will take some work; however, if you╞re able to master the basics covered in this class, you╞ll gain a concrete, marketable skill that may very well be extremely useful in your academic and professional life.On the statistical side, we╞ll cover basic topics from statistics and probability that are required to argue persuasively using data (a list of some of the topics to be covered can be found below). ß This is not a ⌠typical÷ Statistics 101 class; instead of covering an exhaustive list of topics and asking you to memorize many formulas, our goal is to focus only on the most important topics for convincingly analyzing data now by solving ⌠hands on÷ weekly data puzzles.This class is taught in unique manner √ students have to solve ⌠data puzzles÷ (one or more weekly) and ßdefend their solutions in class in the so called ⌠Court of Data÷. ß ß Students compete in the semester long competition for the titles of Data Masters (aggregated score for all data puzzles and the project)One of the objectives of the class is to show the danger of false, random conclusions from data and learning right methodology of ⌠healthy skepticism÷.We will also discuss how not to be fooled by data and show examples of rushed and ad hoc conclusions from so called ⌠big data÷ in the news and on the web. ßIn addition we will examine both upside and downside of big data on the web. ßWe will talk about privacy, anonymity ßvs personalization and data ownership when we increasingly rely on online services.In Final project ß your data findings should have real consequences, preferably ⌠actionable÷ and consequential in the real society.
Tomasz Imielinski
True
True
Computer Application for Business
170
Introduction to business application of spreadsheet software, computer technology, data communications, network applications, and structured programming.
Frances Trees
True
False
Introduction to Discrete Structures I
205
To introduce the student to the mathematical tools of logic and induction, and to the basic definitions and theorems concerning relations, functions, and sets. Later courses in the computer science curriculum build on the mathematical foundations covered here. Particular emphasis is placed on inductive definitions and proofs, with application to problems in computer science.
Swastik Kopparty, Jeffrey Ames
False
True
Introduction to Discrete Structures II
206
Provides the background in combinatorics and probability theory required in design and analysis of algorithms, in system analysis, and in other areas of computer science.
Konstantinos Michmizos
False
True
Data Management for Data Science
210
This course is intended to be the third offering in the sequence of courses for the SAS Data Science Certificate program. It is designed to provide students with the knowledge and skills needed to acquire and curate real word data, to explore the data to discover patterns and distributions, and to manage large datasets with databases.Students will learn the minimal aspects of Python as needed to acquire and curate datasets. Much of their work will be done using Python libraries that deliver maximum benefit with minimal programming effort: to get data from various online data sources online, detect which aspects of data are uncurated or unreliable and understand why it is so, learn various domain independent and domain dependent ways to curate the data, and get the curated data into a form that can be explored, managed and analyzed. Students will also learn how to get datasets into database-ready form and do basic analysis of such datasets using relational databases and SQL, and NoSQL databases.The course content is designed to be accessible to all SAS students regardless of their major. Although the course has CS 111 as one of the pre-requisites (for Computer Science students), it does not require students to have any programming experience, since in the other pre-requisite course (CS 142), students are only nominally exposed to R.
Sesh Venugopal
True
False
Computer Architecture
211
This course covers the fundamental issues in the design of modern computer systems, including the design and implementation of key hardware components such as the processor, memory, and I/O devices, and the software/hardware interface.
Yipeng Huang, David Menendez
True
True
Software Methodology
213
This course teaches essential principles, techniques, tools, and methods used to develop large software programs in Java. These include object-oriented programming and design, Unified Modeling Language (UML), testing and debugging, using and documenting APIs, asynchronous (event-driven) programming in a Graphical Use Interface (GUI) framework, code maintenance and version management using CVS, software development using Eclipse, introduction to building software on mobile platforms, introduction to multithreading and network programming, object persistence,
Sesh Venugopal, Lily Chang
True
True
Systems Programming
214
This course teaches students how to think about, build, debug, and test large computer programs. The course stresses learning how to use tools such as debuggers, profilers, source version control systems, and integrated development environments as an essential part of developing large programs. The course also stresses the understanding of how programs execute on today's computers and how to measure and optimize performance. Programming will be in C on Unix systems to introduce students to a new programming eco system, as well as enable the mapping of high-level language constructs to the underlying machine.
John-Austen Francisco
True
True
Principles of Programming Languages
314
Students explore procedures and parameter passing techniques, essential components of function invocation and control flow in programming languages. The course covers type systems, type checking, and type equivalence, crucial for ensuring program correctness and robustness
He Zhu, John-Austen Francisco
True
False
Numerical Analysis and Computing
323
To expose the student to the development, application, and analysis of basic numerical algorithms.
Mridul Aanjaneya
True
True
Introduction to Imaging and Multimedia
334
Introduces fundamental techniques and concepts used in computational imaging and multimedia.ßßUpon completion, a successful student will be able to design and implement programs that deal with image, video, and audio data.
Ahmed Elgammal
True
True
Principles of Information and Data Management
336
Describing and querying various forms of information such as structured data in relational databases, unstructured text (IR), semi-structured data (XML, web), deductive knowledge. Conceptual modeling and schema design. Basics of database management system services (transactions, reliability, security, optimization). Advanced topics: finding patterns in data, information mapping and integration. The course focuses on a user's perspective, rather than how one implements DBMS.
Antonio Miranda Garcia
True
True
Design and Analysis of Computer Algorithms
344
To study a variety of useful algorithms and analyze their complexity; by that experience to gain insight into principles and data-structures useful in algorithm design.
Sepehr Assadi, Aaron Bernstein
True
True
Internet Technology
352
To provide a practical understanding of computer networks with respect to system architectures, protocols, and client-server interaction.ßßThese objectives are accomplished through extensive laboratory exercises.
Srinivas Narayana
True
True
Seminar in Computers and Society
405
To provide a forum for the study and discussion of the impact of computers on humans and society. For students interested in exploring social, ethical,scientific, and practical implications of the recentweb-based technologies and systems.
Casimir Kulikowski
False
True
Compilers
415
To reveal the general concepts and theoretical foundations of programming language translation and implementation.ßßEmphasis will be placed on imperative languages.Recommended for all students interested in programming languages and techniques used to build software tools (i.e., debuggers, browsers).
Uli Kremer
True
True
Operating Systems Design
416
To convey a thorough understanding of the basics of an operating system by studying techniques and algorithms for providing services in a computer system, and to understand implementation aspects of popular systems by means of case studies.
Badri Nath
True
True
Distributed Systems: Concepts and Design
417
Provides an introduction to design principles and concepts of distributed computer systems. The course covers a broad spectrum of topics encompassing system architecture, software abstractions, distributed algorithms, and issues pertaining to distributed environments such as security and fault tolerance.Topics will range from the theoretical to the practical with a strong emphasis on the practical, such as client-server programming, remote procedure/method calls, multicasting, firewall design, distributed file systems, machine virtualization, clustering, cryptography, and authentication protocols.
Paul Krzyzanowski
True
True
Computer Security
419
This course is an undergraduate-level introduction to computer security and is targeted towards seniors and advanced juniors.
Shiqing Ma
True
True
Brain-Inspired Computing
425
The course explores how computation in the human brain can be effectively modeled across the main levels of abstraction (from a single neuron to biological neural networks and system; introduces a time-sensitive computational formalization of brain function based on the model of neuron as a Spike Processing Machine √ Spike Neural Networks (SNNs); and employs neuro-mimetic or neuro-inspired SNNs to tackle a problem in a term-wide project. The aim of this course is to provide the student with a solid foundation in the field.
Konstantinos Michmizos
True
True
Introduction to Computer Graphics
428
To provide a broad introduction to the field of Computer Graphics, and to describe the techniques that are commonly used in the graphics industry today (such as in production of special effects, computer animation, 3D interactive games, and VR).
Mridul Aanjaneya
True
True
Software Engineering
431
The course studies the problems, methods, processes and tools involved in the development of large software systems that are reliable and maintainable, and meet their users' needs. This is carried out in the context of a significant, term-long multi-person team project.(In different semesters, this course would focus on either morestandard, centralized systems, or distributed systems. This wouldeffect, to some extent, the choice of topics to be taught (see below),and especially the techniques and tools to be used.)
Lily Chang
True
True
Introduction to Data Science
439
This course covers topics needed to solve problems involving data, which includes preparation (collection and integration), characterization and presentation (information visualization), analysis (machine learning and data mining), and products (applications).
Andy Gunawardena
True
True
Introduction to Artificial Intelligence
440
To provide a broad introduction to Artificial Intelligence. The course will cover both fundamental concepts such as search and knowledge representation, as well as applied work in areas such as planning and vision. This course is intended for both students majoring in Computer Science as well as nonspecialists with the necessary background who wish to acquire a general familiarity withßArtificial Intelligence.
Troy Mcmahon
True
True
